this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
as a radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the party
hello listeners Marcus here I wanted to
ask you a favor
we are looking for somebody who helps us
get rid of the spam on the website you
might have noticed that the comments on
the SEO radio website are full of spam
some of it you know bunch of strange
Chinese letters that you can't even read
others seem rather sensible where the
common kind of takes into account
although it's spam it still takes into
account somehow some of the keywords of
the episode but then there is still a
spam link so we're looking for somebody
who helps us get rid of this stuff let's
call this person that these spammy fire
this is your chance to contribute to su
radio your job would be to basically
subscribe to the comments feed and take
a look at the comments and if they are
crap
go to the website log in and delete it
and you would obviously do us and
especially the community a great favor
so if you're interested in helping us in
this respect send an email to team at se
- radio dotnet we'd obviously greatly
appreciate your help okay that's all I
wanted to say let's go on to the content
of this episode welcome to a new episode
on software engineering radio our topic
today is the difference between software
engineering and computer science on the
microphone is Michael and my guest today
is Chuck Cano NSA radio we noticed an
article at the dr. Dobbs Journal on this
topic so we contacted Chuck and asked
him whether he would volunteer for an
interview on the same topic Chuck
welcome on the show thank you thank you
very much
would you like to briefly introduce
yourself as Michael said my name is
Chuck Connell I work in the Boston area
and I have been working in computer
science and software development for
about 25 years as a as a combination I
have kind of a foot
in the practical applied world I am a
software developer I'm a software
consultant I've worked in a number of
technologies over the years as well as
I've been involved in the academic world
of computer science I have a graduate
degree in computer science from Boston
University and have continued to take
courses over the years beyond that
degree so I've always had an interest in
the kind of the theoretical academic
world as well as applied applied
programming topics in your article you
state something along the lines that
software engineering doesn't really fit
into computer science because it it's
inherently different it's it's too soft
it's too unpredictable it has no sound
theory around it how would you summarize
your your statement in that paper yes I
think what you said is accurate let me
give a little background on that there
is some attempt by some researchers in
software engineering to make software
development software engineering more
more rigorous and provable and provably
correct than it is now I mean as
everybody knows now software development
projects sometimes they go right
sometimes they go wrong sometimes they
finish on time sometimes they they take
five times longer than then we thought
they would and so obviously it would be
it would be a great thing if software
development were were more rigorous more
well-defined if we developed code in a
more provably correct way you know that
would obviously be be good for everybody
so there are some researchers in the
field who are trying to make software
more math software development more
mathematical more rigorous and and
that's so that's sort of the the
background of my article and in my
article I argue that while
some aspects of computer science
certainly are useful to software
engineers and that a good software
engineer should know some of that
background that in the end software
development is never going to be
rigorously who rigorously provable and
reason is that that people are involved
in software development are and are a
crucial part of the software development
process so it it will never be rigorous
and mathematical like some other areas
of computer science are no I could
challenge so why did you even expect to
be it provable to be predictable as the
other does of disciplines within
computer science they might be well the
answer to that is that there are some
efforts not certainly not by everyone
but by some people within the software
engineering field to do just that to
define rigorous methods of software
development that that do make it
provably correct and formal formal
development methods is one way there's a
link in my article on dr. Dobbs journal
to some good information from the US
government agency NASA I believe it's at
Langley Air Force Base and there's a
link in there to some of these formal
methods another buzzword people might
have heard about his cleanroom
engineering so there there are efforts
to make the whole software development
process correct and provably correct
so my articles is responding in a sense
to that to that effort so do you believe
in clean room development and those
formal methods I remember for example
the specification language set from my
studies I believe in them in a sense I
that any software development method
clean room formal agile extreme
you know whatever you want that they are
all useful in the right context applied
to the right projects but I do not
believe in talent your questions right I
do not believe in formal development
methods or cleanroom in the sense that
they can ever give us what they promise
which is provably correct software I
don't believe in them in that sense at
least not as at a reasonable stay a
scale I would expect that it works for
some tiny examples but not really for
any realistic application as we know it
from our desktop PCs right yeah
absolutely I agree sure you can you know
we can define an example of some small
program we want and express it in some
rigorous semantic language and develop a
provably correct piece of software for
it sure it'll work on some example but
but I claim it it will never scale to
real examples was there any trigger any
event that led you to writing this
article or was it just well I had
planned it for years and out I just do
it I guess there were two triggers the
first is kind of four years as I said
I've kind of had a foot in both worlds
of practical software development as
well as academic computer science and it
always it always was frustrating to me
and I and it's frustrating to many many
people that when you work on a on a real
software project it never goes as nicely
as as formal computer science for
instance I'm thinking to say of analysis
of algorithms for instance or
cryptographic analysis you know those
are areas where you get provably correct
results
and or some areas of compiler theory for
instance and you know it's always
frustrating for everybody developing
real-world practical software that it
never goes that well and bugs come up
and it takes longer and so there's you
know I and many other people have
frustration that practical development
doesn't go as well as theory sometimes
and then and then I guess the other kind
of short term trigger is I was having a
conversation I cite him in the paper
with a one of my professors Steve Steven
Homer who is a theorist who is a formal
computer science theorist and we were
talking about the difference between
practical software development and
regular computer science theory and that
kind of triggered that kind of triggered
the article that I wrote how would you
separate actually the two topics from
each other
I would well thinking about it I see
them intermingled in many aspects can
you draw a clear line between both
topics yes I think I can and there's
actually a diagram in my article that
makes this point I brief note we include
that in there so no sure
I that the difference between practical
software development and formal computer
science and and that really includes all
the areas of formal computer science is
the fact that software engineering and
software development involve people in
their process and what we study in
school as traditional computer science
does not crucially involve people and
I'm looking at the diagram from the
article which I understand is in the
show notes
so for instance areas of computer
science such as queuing theory
algorithms machine learning complexity
network analysis those topics do not
involve a person crucially in the
subject matter
and you can people study those subjects
but they are true or correct or not
correct regardless of a person being in
the middle whereas at the top of the
diagram their subjects such as usability
requirements engineering scalability
estimation design patterns those topics
crucially involve people you know people
are you cannot study those topics
without studying the people that are
involved in the software process so you
know I feel that in my opinion that's
that's the bright line between what's
traditionally considered software
engineering and what's traditionally
considered computer science could you
maybe go one level deeper sure I have
something I have some examples let's
make it concrete with two examples the
first is the problem of estimating in
software development every software
every real software project you know
other than some small piece of homework
we're doing in a class every real piece
of software development we want to
estimate how long it's going to take
because if the answer is that it's going
to take a week it's going to take say
one person a week will say sure let's go
ahead and do it if the answer is that
it's going to take twenty people five
years we might say no that's not worth
it so estimation is crucial in
everywhere world software project when
we need to know how long software is
going to take to decide if it's worth it
or not and estimation by its very nature
means how long are people this team of
people going to spend doing this project
and I claim and I think it's
self-evident that there's no rigorous
mathematical method or recipe that we
are ever going to have that's going to
produce accurate estimates for how long
some team of people is going to take to
do some piece of software I mean even
imagine
you have a crack team that has turned
out many good software projects before
let's say a team of 10 people but
partway through the project five of them
gets sick or lose interest in software
development well your estimate is out
the window and you know no formal system
can capture that now I should add within
estimation there there are some fairly
well-developed estimating techniques
such as Kokomo and I think I have a link
in the article about that that try to
apply some formulas and mathematical
heuristics to estimation but if you look
close and and some of they have these
very complex daunting formulas that look
very scientific but if you look closely
at that work it's really still a
guesstimate I mean those those formulas
are involved there are based on previous
projects by similar teams and can easily
go wrong and the formulas even involve
all sorts of scaling factors that are
extremely subjective so these seemingly
rigorous estimating methods are not if
you look at it closely or not as
rigorous as they appear so I think
estimation is an area where there will a
m-- there will never be a rigorous
provable exact method for doing it the
other example is what is often called
modify ability or maintainability or
extensibility I'll kind of lump those
all together those properties of
software we want software to be
modifiable because we think of a new
feature or we change an existing feature
we want to be maintainable because
there's going to be bugs to fix and
extensible we want to you know add some
new feature or scale it in some way so
this is surely a property that we want
out of out of any real software that we
care about
but the question of how maintainable
modifiable a piece of software is
crucially involves the people who are
working on it because if you have a bug
to fix what do you do well you sit down
and you look at the software and you try
to understand what's going on there and
and understand what's causing the bug or
even or if you know what's causing the
bug you try to understand where the fix
needs to be apply well that's a human
process and I can't imagine any formal
system that's going to tell us how to
construct software so it looks more
clear to the people who have to maintain
it it's it's just crucially kind of
bound up with the way people think so to
me that's another example where you know
formal systems will never give us
everything we want in software
development another example you
mentioned in your article is CMM I the
capability maturity model of the
software engineering Institute well at
least what what I know about it you get
a number out of it so how can you come
up with a number from something that is
not really touchable graspable how do
they do that and what do what is their
trick to come up with a number
yeah the CMMI I actually I'm actually
believer in that and let me take that
from the other side
CMMI which is capability maturity model
and there's various flavors of that
comes out of the software engineering
Institute at Carnegie Mellon University
in Pittsburgh and CMMI actually is not a
rigorous method although it's very long
and very heavy when you get the printed
version and can be difficult to read and
and some teams of software developers
love it and some hate it but its goal is
not to be a rigorous method its goal
is really to be a set of best practices
that have turned out to work well for
other teams of software developers so I
actually believe that they're on the
right track there they're not trying to
be provably correct the thing is the
text is not filled with mathematical
formulas you know it is very long it is
very difficult to read in places but
their goal is a template of development
methods that have been found to be good
really best practices at a number of
previous sites and and they're always
tweaking it you know that I mean they
have the right spirit that you know they
never thought it was correct 20 years
ago or 10 years ago they're always
tweaking and it always learning so you
know I think they have the right spirit
although it's it's gotten kind of big
and an onerous you mentioned now several
times the best practices for example in
the context of patterns and software
design you mentioned it for CMM I so it
seems like best practices is the middle
ground as good as it can get
with software engineering to make it
somehow structured yes I think that's
right I think that I mean I think you
know middle ground is the right word you
know we don't want to say and we don't
want to say there's nothing we can ever
learn about software development and
every project is something new from
scratch and we have no idea how to do
software development well you know we
clearly don't want to say that and
that's clearly not true on the other
hand I maintain in this article that we
can never make software provably correct
but the middle ground is just what you
said patterns of software development
that have been found to work well on
past projects and patterns also when you
read that literature patterns work well
for certain kinds of programs and
patterns always say where they are
applicable
where they make sense or they should say
that and so patterns are kind of best
practice and and patterns can apply it
kind of at the co.design level or higher
up at the architecture level and the
idea is the same it's it's it's best
practices things that have been learned
on previous projects CMMI is that as
well
agile techniques extreme programming
those are again best practices that have
worked well in the past that have a good
chance of working well on your new
project especially if you understand
where what kinds of projects they should
be applied to so I think I mean I think
that's the right way to look at software
engineering to instead of trying to
develop techniques to provably correct
which I maintain will never work we can
learn we can develop wisdom and best
practices over time so is that something
like a conclusion or what what we learn
now after we observed as difference
between computer science and software
engineering just difference and and
matter and behavior and structured Ness
and predictability yes I think I mean I
think the difference is you know let's
take a topic like you know cryptography
or say register allocation in compiler
theory you can get correct your results
in those areas and for those questions
or at least for some of those questions
in software engineering I think correct
results are you know nearly impossible
in every situation unless you define the
problem very very narrowly but what we
can get is best practices body of
knowledge built up over time you know
experience that that works well going
forward
can we get better at that should we get
better with that do you know or do you
see any holes where we don't make the
best out of what we have today with
software engineering what would be your
recommendation well there's a good
questions I guess there's kind of two
parts there can we get better absolutely
I mean look at other areas of
engineering such as bridges you know
bridges over over rivers and you know
Rockets space rockets those areas of
engineering they get better all the time
you know occasionally there are failures
you you still see bridges that collapse
but people have gotten better at that
you know every year more or less as time
has gone on you know in the same thing
with rocket technology and I certainly
expect software to continue to do that I
think the whole area of patterns is a
fairly recent area in software
engineering and and a lot of good has
come out of that so I think that you
know I think we certainly can get better
any holes that's that's a good question
I have to think on that a bit you know
are there areas where there are still
holes in our knowledge I know there's
good good question I don't have an
immediate answer on that one
you mentioned that software engineering
as software development is an
engineering discipline now if you would
have to decide between the terms science
art or craftsmanship for the act of
software development
what would you relate it more to
craftsmanship you know I can I imagine
for instance a skilled woodworker a
cabinet maker you know someone who is a
good woodworker certainly knows the
technical details they understand the
materials involved the wood the tools
the way
the tools in the wood and the glue and
the materials interact they understand
structural engineering of putting
together something with wood those
things are absolutely required of a good
craftsman but craftsmanship also
involves more than that it's experience
built up over time it's a sense of the
artistic a sense of design that you know
only people can understand so I like the
term I like to turn craftsmanship for
for good software development yes I
totally agree so I like to challenge you
on that and so that is a typical
question you would ask at a beer in the
evening with some friends together with
some geek friends and you could get
lively discussions on that but as you
said it I believe it's it's the
experience for one which really helps in
developing good software reliable
software and the other part that I think
is important there's also some some
beauty and simplicity in it as with
craftsmanship I mean you can solve and
create any kind of thing but it also
matters how you do it how this piece of
wood afterwards looks but it looks like
a chair or something that you hardly can
identify as a chair yet but you might be
you might potentially be able to sit on
it right that's right and in fact this
sort of touches on something we talked
about in our email B before this
interview which is education you know in
the ideal world
how should software engineers be trained
you know what should it look like to go
to school to study software engineering
software development and I think that in
my opinion software engineering
development should be more than a subset
of computer science
I mean a good software developer
absolutely needs to know some computer
science they need to know analysis of
algorithms they need to know complexity
they need to know programming language
theory absolutely there are areas of
formal computer science that a good
software engineer should know but that's
not the whole story
and software engineers also need to know
management techniques how to work in
teams a little bit of psychology user
psychology as well as team psychology so
in my ideal world software engineering
would be would be taught not completely
separately from computer science but but
recognizing that it has a different
focus making it the first-class citizen
that universe right actually and I know
it's somewhere hidden in any CS
department yeah that's right yeah that's
right I agree with that I mean I I
remember saying me that and in one of
the earlier episodes but I really
believe good software developers don't
just come easily out of computer science
studies but there there needs to be more
on that either I have a really strong
education on software engineering you've
gotten that at during your studies at
university or really do do a lots of
practical world practical work to learn
on it and and get experience and
knowledge on it right and that's right
and I think both are needed I mean
imagine I could imagine somebody for
instance who is very very good at formal
say complexity theory you know analyzing
the complexity of some algorithms or you
know looking at the mathematics of
what's computable what's not computable
I can imagine somebody who's very good
at that but is not a very good software
engineer because
they're not good at communicating with
users to understand what they want or
not good at working in teams and I mean
we need people you know we need people
of all types and on the other hand a
software engineer does need to know some
of some of the rigorous theory as well
so you know there's there's an overlap
but but they're different skill sets now
we talked a lot about education at
University how about really the
application of software engineering in
industry in in daily life or building
real-world products do we need to change
something after this knowledge after
this observation you thinking of how
sort of ongoing education for people who
have been working in the field ongoing
education or do we treat software
development right in industry today in
general I mean looking back at your
experiences from from IBM or other big
large companies I think that I think
part of the answer is that if software
development were taught as as we're both
suggesting more as a first class citizen
more as its own discipline I think that
would help I mean what happens now is
that many people doing real-world
software development have a computer
science background a computer science
degree from somewhere and again that's
valuable that helps to some extent but I
would like to see software engineering
curriculums include more than just that
and you know and I think that would help
that would help going forward and I mean
one view one view of computer science
that I I partly believe is that computer
science core computer science really is
a branch of mathematics now I mean I
didn't make that up I'm you know I'm
quoting something I've heard there and
and I think there's some truth to that
and you know and that's interesting and
that's valuable for people who want to
study that and and I've studied those
subjects and I've enjoyed them but you
know we should recognize that
you know doing real-world software
development is more than just a branch
of mathematics so do you have any other
related discussions or recommendations
on on literature and ideas around that
topic you send me an advance a set of
links we will which we all will include
in in the show notes but any
recommendations on interesting topics
from you let me just mention those links
briefly of what people can find there
soon the the article I wrote that that
prompted this podcast is there and Grady
Booch there's a very interesting site
there what what he has done is collected
interesting software architectures and I
think this is the kind of thing that
that people use as an input to design
patterns but his goal there is to kind
of build up a shared knowledge of the
way people have approached difficult
interesting software projects Steve
McConnell who wrote rapid development as
well as after the gold rush and several
of these a very well-known author in
software engineering his blog is listed
there and and there's a lot of good
stuff in there also the page from NASA
about formal software methods is there
and that's interesting to look through
and I think you've also posted my
website called beautiful software comm
where I've collected my essays on this
topic and others about software
development what kind of a says no you
make me curious well I've been writing
for a number of years about software
engineering so there's this article as
well there's another piece that I just
finished and will come out in dr. Dobbs
this month about refactoring we haven't
talked about it yet in this in this
broadcast but the whole refactoring
movement and I kind of summarized what
that is and and talk about some some
background theory for refactoring is
there so this month is September yes in
case we publish does episode fine the my
understanding is that that
peace will appear during September on
dr. Dobbs September 2009 system 2009
correct
and I wrote a number of pieces about the
process of open source development which
is also listed there and had a an online
debate with Eric Raymond who's who's
well known in that field about the
process of open source development and
that that material is on that website as
well okay lots of interesting links and
things to look at any final comment from
your side I think that just about covers
it I'm always interested in hearing from
readers or listeners you know with their
comments or links I've you know over the
years I've been writing I've often
improved an article or tweaked an
article based on some feedback I got
from somebody so you know I welcome
people to give me feedback there's my
contact information is is on that site
beautiful software comm and also please
use the comment feature at our se Radio
absolutely dotnet comment infrastructure
okay
alright thanks Chuck for this interview
thank you Michael
bye-bye okay
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio software engineer
radio is an educational program brought
to you by hillside Europe if you want
more information about the podcast and
all the other episodes visit our website
at se - radio dotnet if you want to
support us you can donate to the AC
radio team by our website or you can
advertise for se radio for example by
clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
links and the slash dot button to
contact the team please send email to
team at SC - radio net or if they're
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under the
creative comments 2.5 license please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the pot size Music
Network for the music used in this show
the song is called Vegas Achtung